(dramatic music)
- On July 19, 1989,
United Airlines Flight 232
takes off from Denver, Colorado
heading towards Chicago.
It's been nearly an hour since departure
and the plane is now flying over Iowa
with a sunny, clear sky and
relatively no turbulence.
By all accounts, it's a routine flight
with two very experienced pilots
and one flight engineer in the cockpit.
The plane is on autopilot
and is now doing a turn towards
a heading of 95 degrees.
But then suddenly, with a violent jolt,
everything changes.
The plane is a DC-10
and it is outfitted with three engines,
one underneath each wing
and a third at the base of the tail fin
towards the back of the plane.
After hearing and feeling
the explosive bang,
flight engineer Dudley Dvorak reports
that it is the rear
engine that has failed.
Copilot William Records
takes control of the plane
as Captain Alfred Haynes
begins an engine shutdown checklist.
(pensive music)
Though it is alarming to
lose an engine mid flight,
it isn't the worst case scenario.
The DC-10 is designed to still be able
to fly even if only two
engines are operational,
and so the crew is able to cut off power
to the damaged engine
and turn their attention to
steadying the plane back out.
But this is when they realize
just how bad the situation actually is
because even though the plane
is able to continue flying,
Copilot Records reports
that none of the controls are working.
Captain Haynes attempts to
manipulate the controls as well
and confirms that nothing
seems to be functional.
While the two pilots continue flying
to see why the plane isn't responding
to the controls, Flight
Engineer Dvorak comes up
with their answer.
The plane has lost all hydraulic fluid.
(dramatic music)
Hydraulic fluid is needed
for nearly every control
output on the plane.
For example, in order to make
a plane bank to the left,
a pilot will turn the
control column to the left,
causing the left aileron to move up
and the right aileron to move down.
The hydraulic fluid is
a pressurized liquid
that allows these ailerons
to move up and down
once the control column is moved.
If there is no fluid, there's no pressure
that forces this movement,
no matter how hard the control column
is turned left or right.
Now, because hydraulic
pressure is so vital
to flying a plane,
there are actually three
separate hydraulic lines
that run through a DC-10.
These hydraulic systems are
independent from one another
so that if one should
fail, there are two others
that can continue
providing hydraulic power.
There is no procedure to
follow should all three fail
because the likelihood of
this happening was thought
to be one in a billion,
virtually impossible.
And with no hydraulic fluid left,
the plane begins banking to the right.
If this continues, the plane is in danger
of fully rolling over,
a situation that there's
no recovering from.
Flight 232 will crash.
(dramatic music)
Thinking quickly, Captain Hayes realizes
that even without hydraulic fluid,
they still have at least one control
that they can manipulate:
the engine throttles.
By decreasing the power
to the left engine,
Haynes is able to slowly
level the plane back out.
(dramatic music continues)
And with the immediate danger addressed,
the crew can now turn their
attention to the bigger issue:
they have no way to fly this plane.
(suspenseful music)
Now, what the flight crew don't realize
is that even though all
three hydraulic lines
run separately, there is one section
in the back of the plane
where they come within close
proximity near the rear engine.
Later investigations will
reveal that within the engine,
a fan disc had been produced using metal
that was not completely pure
and this manufacturing
defect went unnoticed.
A crack began to form with
each flight the aircraft took
until finally the disc
couldn't hold anymore
and broke apart within the engine.
The resulting explosion
severed the hydraulic lines
to this rear engine,
but it also sent shrapnel
flying all around the area
towards the same section
where the other two hydraulic
lines come close together,
severing them as well.
The result was all lines
bleeding hydraulic fluid
until they were empty, leaving
the flight crew helpless.
At this very moment, a flight
attendant comes to the cockpit
to get an update on the situation.
She can immediately
tell things aren't good,
and this is confirmed
when Haynes tells her
to ready the cabin for
an emergency landing.
Once she returns and begins instructing
the other flight attendants
to follow suit, she is stopped
by a passenger sitting near
the back of first class.
He asks for information
about what is going on
and he seems relatively
calm given the situation.
That is because he is
no ordinary passenger.
His name is Dennis Fitch
and he himself is a pilot,
but not just any pilot.
Fitch is actually a flight
instructor for the DC-10,
the very aircraft that they are onboard.
The flight attendant tells him
that the rear engine has shut down
and that the captain has reported
that all hydraulics are lost.
Now, Fitch can't believe what he's hearing
as he knows this aircraft in and out
and understands just how
unlikely that could be.
And yet if it is true, he also knows
that they are almost certainly doomed
because he has studied a previous flight
that has had this exact same problem.
(airplane whooshing)
(dramatic music)
Just four years before
United Flight 232 departed
on its fated flight, Japan
Airlines Flight 123 takes off
from Tokyo en route to Osaka.
It'll be a short flight, about one hour,
but nonetheless, the journey
will be made on a Boeing 747.
These aircraft are known
for their large size
and are more typically used
for long distance flights.
However, this particular 747 variant
is one specifically
requested by Japan Airlines
in response to high demand
for certain domestic routes,
such as between Tokyo and Osaka.
With this model, fuel capacity
is reduced in exchange
for strengthening the
structure of the aircraft
to accommodate more frequent
takeoffs and landings.
And because it will be
used for shorter flights,
the business class section is reduced
and the economy section is increased,
allowing for more seats overall.
No other airplane type had a
higher capacity at the time
as this 747SR carried
a staggering 524 people
on this flight.
But what no one on board knows
is that something is happening
in the back of the plane.
Just a few years prior,
this particular 747 was
involved in a hard landing
that resulted in a tail strike.
There were even some
injuries but no casualties
and the plane needed some serious repairs,
especially to the pressure bulkhead
in the back of the plane.
This is a curved wall that
separates the pressurized air
in the cabin from non-pressurized
air, acting as a seal.
Now, half of this bulkhead was damaged
during the tail strike, and
so repairs were carried out.
The lower half dome of this
bulkhead was therefore replaced,
but this is where the
fix wasn't done properly.
In the correct installation,
a single splice plate is used
to connect both the upper and
lower half of the bulkhead.
This way, the loads are transmitted evenly
across three rows of rivets.
But during the repair, instead
of using one single sheet,
the splice plate was cut into two parts.
This is a big mistake.
The top rivet is essentially
not carrying any load
as it's not even connected to
the lower bulkhead anymore.
And so with each flight after the repair,
cracks began to form around this area,
and every flight the plane took,
pressurizing and depressurizing the cabin,
the cracks grew worse and worse.
It was only a matter of time
until the bulkhead couldn't hold anymore.
(dramatic music)
Only 12 minutes into Flight 123,
all 524 occupants feel an
explosive decompression
as the pressure bulkhead fractures.
Pressurized air rushes into
the space behind the bulkhead,
an area not designed
to handle the instantaneous
pressure change.
This causes more ruptures
in the back of the plane
and the vertical tail fin
blows off the aircraft.
(fin exploding)
- [Flight Crew 1] Hey,
something has exploded!
Squawk 77.
The gear door! Check the gears.
- What?
- Check the gears!
- The engine?
- Squawk 77.
- [Host] The explosion is so sudden
that everything takes place
in less than half a second
and oxygen masks drop as the
cabin becomes depressurized.
(flight crew speaking in Japanese)
- The flight crew immediately calls out
to the Tokyo control tower
and requests authorization
to return to the airport.
- [Control Tower] Tokyo, Japan Air 123,
request, immediate, ah,
ah, trouble, request to
return back to Haneda.
Descend and maintain 220. Over.
- [Captain] Roger,
approved as you requested.
- Permission is granted,
though now the crew realizes a problem
because just like United Flight 232,
all hydraulic lines have
been severed in the explosion
caused by shrapnel
flying out in the section
where the lines come close together.
The plane has become unflyable.
(airplane engine roaring)
- [Flight Crew] All the
hydraulic systems have gone dead?
But, now uncontrollable.
- [Flight Crew] Uncontrollable,
roger, understood.
- With no controls and
now a missing tail fin,
the plane begins dipping forward and back.
This is called phugoid motion.
Essentially, as the plane
descends, it gains air speed,
but this additional speed causes lift,
which makes the plane climb.
With no control surfaces
to correct this motion,
the plane continuously rises
and dips in a wave-like pattern.
The flight crew realizes
that the only control they still
have left is engine thrust,
and so they begin increasing
and decreasing the plane's four engines,
an attempt to steer back to towards Tokyo.
If they want to take a right turn,
they increase power on the left engines
and lower power on the right.
It is an extremely difficult process,
but even still, the crew is able
to make some progress
in getting turned around
to head back to Haneda Airport,
and they are decreasing their altitude.
But now they have yet another
problem looming ahead of them:
the Japanese Alps.
(plane whooshing)
(warning beeping)
- [Flight Crew 1] Hey,
there's a mountain ahead.
- [Flight Crew 2] I know.
- [Flight Crew 1] Turn
right. It's a mountain there.
- [Flight Crew  2] I know, Sir.
- [Flight Crew 1] Take control,
to the right, right turn!
- [Flight Crew 2] Right
turn, that's right?
- We could hit the mountain.
- I know.
- [Flight Crew 1] Right turn.
(plane warning beeping)
Left turn.
Put more power on. Left turn now!
Left turn!
(dramatic music)
- With little ability
to control the plane,
the crew do all they can
to avoid the mountains.
Ultimately, there's
nothing that can be done.
Bracing for impact,
the plane crashes into a ridge
just north of Mount Mikuni
after nearly 30 minutes of
flying an uncontrollable plane.
(plane warning beeping)
- [Flight Crew 1] Nose up!
Power!
(plane warning beeping)
- [Airplane] Bank angle.
(plane alarms blaring)
Pull up!
- [Crew Member 1] It's the end!
- [Plane] Pull up.
Pull up.
(plane crashing)
(pensive music)
- Rescuers immediately
dispatch to the area.
But the situation is dire.
The 747 crashed high in the mountains,
far past the point any
road or path would reach.
And with the sun taking away
the last bit of daylight,
it is virtually impossible
to land a helicopter near the crash site.
After flying over the burning debris,
rescuers believe it is impossible
that anyone could have survived.
Nearly 14 hours after the
crash, with the rising sun,
rescuers finally reach the crash site
and here they discover
a miracle: movement.
They find a woman alive,
though severely injured,
and now seeing there is
hope, the search is energized
and they find a child stuck in a tree.
Searching more, they also find a mother
and her daughter alive,
trapped under debris.
Though miraculous that
four people have survived,
it is coupled with the
devastating realization
that all 520 other occupants
of Flight 123 have perished.
And even more tragic is that
doctors would later determine
that more could have survived
if rescuers had reached
the crash site sooner.
And with so many casualties,
this crash becomes the deadliest one
involving a single plane in
history, even until this day.
(screen whooshing)
(pensive music)
Back on board United Flight
232, just four years later,
Flight Instructor Denny
Fitch is more aware
of this than any other passenger.
Knowing that the Japan Airlines
flight faced the same issue
of losing all hydraulics,
Fitch decides to offer his
assistance to the flight crew,
help that Captain Haynes readily accepts.
- [Flight Crew 1] Very
little elevator or rudder.
Ah, shit.
- [Flight Crew 2] I'll tell you what.
We'll have a beer when this is all done.
- [Flight Crew 1] Well, I don't drink
but I'll sure as hell have one.
Little right turns.
(dramatic music)
- [Host] Haynes explains to Fitch
that they have been using
differential engine thrust
to fly until this point.
- [Flight Crew 1] Come on, baby.
- [Flight Crew 3] What's
the hydraulic quantity?
- [Flight Crew 4] Low zero.
- All of them?
- All of them.
- [Flight Crew 1]
Quantity, quantity is gone.
- [Flight Crew 4] Yeah,
all quantity is gone.
- And Captain Haynes instructs Fitch
to take over so that
he and Copilot Records
can focus on other potential methods
to get the plane safely to the ground.
- [Flight Crew 2] Tell
me, yell what you want
and I'll help you.
- [Flight Crew 1] Right
throttle. Close one, put two up.
- [Host] And so Fitch stands
between the two pilots,
a throttle in each hand, increasing
and decreasing each based on visual cues
and commands from Captain Haynes.
- [Flight Crew 2] United 232
heavy. I understand, sir, uh...
You can only make right turns?
- [Flight Crew 1] That's affirmative.
- With over 400 miles left
until they reach Chicago,
the crew realizes that
they will never make it.
And with help from air traffic control,
they locate a closer
airport they can aim for,
located in Sioux City,
less than 100 miles away.
- [Flight Crew 1] I have serious doubts
about making the airport.
Have you got someplace near there
that we might be able to ditch?
Unless you get control of this airplane,
we're gonna put it down
wherever it happens to be.
- He instructs the flight
attendants to prepare everyone
for a hard crash landing.
- [Flight Crew 1] We're
gonna try and put it
into Sioux City Iowa.
- Yeah.
- [Flight Crew 1] It's gonna
be tough, it's gonna be rough.
- [Flight Attendant] So we're
going to evacuate for sure?
- [Flight Crew 1] The brace.
The brace will be the signal.
It'll be over the PA
system. Brace, brace, brace.
Good luck, sweetheart.
- Thanks, you too!
(tranquil music)
- [Host] Back in the cabin,
the flight attendants begin
instructing passengers
on the positions to maintain
when it's time to brace for impact.
And as they look around,
they are hit with the
startling realization
of just how many children are on board.
As luck would have it,
today is Children's Day,
a promotion from United
where children can fly for only a penny.
There are 52 minors on Flight 232
and many of them are traveling alone.
(tranquil music)
The flight attendants ask
for help from several adult passengers
and everyone cooperates to make sure
that no child is sitting by themselves.
Next, they turn to the four
children who were young enough
to travel without a seat,
those under two years old.
The crew has no choice
but to continue following procedure
and have their parents place
their children on the floor
in front of them and surround
the children with pillows
and hope for the best.
- [Flight Control] United 232 heavy,
you're gonna have to
widen out just slightly
to your left, sir, to
make the turn to final
and also it will take
you away from the city.
- [Flight Crew 1] Whatever you do,
keep us away from the city.
- Back in the cockpit,
the flight crew is steadily
making way towards Sioux City,
but the plane keeps pulling to the right.
And so deciding it would
be best not to fight it,
they corkscrew their way forward
with help from ATC providing directions
and heading information.
They also begin dumping
as much fuel as they can,
trying to decrease their
weight before landing.
And after two right-hand circles,
it's time to do their first left turn
in order to line up with the airport.
(suspenseful music)
But even after completing that turn,
the plane still keeps drifting
to the right, off the
path towards the airport.
And so rather than keep
fighting it, the crew decides
to do another right-hand
loop to get back on track.
- [Air Traffic Control]
United 232 heavy, roger.
The airport's currently
at your 1 o'clock position, 10 miles.
And United 232 heavy,
if you can't make the airport,
sir, there is an interstate
that runs north to south to
the east side of the airport.
It's a four-lane interstate.
- [Flight Crew 1] We're
just passing it right now.
We're gonna try for the airport.
- Finally, about nine
miles out of Sioux City,
the pilots make visual
contact with the airport.
They've managed to make it this far,
but now they have the worst yet to come
as they still need to land.
One other problem is that
without the hydraulics,
the flaps which allow the aircraft
to fly at much slower speeds for takeoff
and landing cannot be extended.
They are, however, able to
manually lower the landing gear,
letting gravity do the work of
locking the wheels in place.
And the extra drag from the landing gear
helps reduce their speed a bit,
but not by much as they
are still going more
than double the speed
of a typical landing.
The entire airport lays open before them
with every runway available.
Sioux City Airport has three runways,
but only two of them
were active at the time
as runway 2/2 had been closed
permanently a year earlier.
The crew hopes to use runway 3/1,
therefore the closed runway 2/2 is used
by emergency responders to set up
and prepare themselves to assist
for what they know will be a bad landing.
But just two minutes before a touchdown,
Captain Haynes realizes that
they aren't lined up at all
for runway 3/1
and they don't have time
to make corrections.
But as luck would have it,
they are lined up almost
perfectly with runway 2/2.
- [Air Traffic Control] United 232 heavy,
the wind's currently
360 at 1 1, 360 at 11.
You're cleared to land on any runway.
(flight crew member 1 chuckling)
- [Flight Crew 1] You wanna be particular
make it a runway, huh?
- [Air Traffic Control] 0 1 0 at 1 1
and there is a runway that's closed, sir
that could probably work too.
It runs northeast to Southwest.
Pretty well lined up on this
one, I think we will be.
- [Host] Immediately responders rush
to clear the closed runway
and make way for the plane.
- [Air Traffic Control]
Sir, that's a closed runway.
That'll work, sir.
We're getting the equipment off the runway
and they'll line up for that one.
- [Flight Crew 1] How long is it?
- [Air Traffic Control]
At the end of the runway,
it's just a wide open field, sir,
so the length won't be a problem.
- And with nothing left they can do,
everyone straps in
and Captain Haynes calls
out to the passengers
to brace themselves.
- [Flight Crew 2] That's
what's turning ya.
- OK.
- Back, Al.
Left throttle, left, left,
left, left, left, left, left.
(plane warning blaring)
- [Plane] Pull up, pull up, pull up.
- [Flight Crew 1] God!
- [Helper 1] Buddy to 19,
he's coming down real
fast down the south end.
- [Helper 2] Okay, all
right, he's going down.
There he goes.
- He's on fire.
(sad music)
- Unfortunately, despite
the crew's best efforts,
the uncontrollable plane
finally gets the best of them.
Just above the ground,
the plane dips sharply to the right
and the right wing strikes the ground.
The plane immediately
begins breaking apart
and ignites in a fireball
as the wreckage continues
skidding down the runway
and into nearby cornfields.
Emergency responders rush to the scene
and everyone fears it'll
be just like Japan Airlines
all over again.
And yet, as they approach,
passengers begin streaming
out of the wreckage.
Responders begin evacuating
and attending to any
survivors they can find,
and survivors themselves
also assist each other.
One man escapes the burning wreckage
only to hear a baby crying
from somewhere in the plane.
Risking his own life, he goes back in
and finds a baby, which
somehow during the impact
became trapped in an overhead bin.
He is able to escape with the child,
reuniting her back with her mother.
And outside responders also
attempt to locate the cockpit,
which broke apart during the impact.
It takes them 40 minutes,
but finally they discover its
broken and charred remains
after seeing Flight Engineer
Dvorak waving his arms
from the wreckage.
Captain Haynes, Copilot
Records, Flight Engineer Dvorak
and Flight Instructor Fitch are all alive,
though in critical condition.
They are freed from the wreckage
and join the other survivors
who are now being raced
to the nearby trauma center.
(tranquil hopeful music)
By the end of the rescue
efforts, it's a bitter moment.
113 people perished after the
crash, including 11 children.
It is a situation
that no one should have walked away from,
a crash that seemed impossible to survive.
And yet 183 people made it.
A combination of skill from
the crew, good communication,
and a little bit of luck
meant that more than half
of Flight 232 live to see another day.
Now, both these crashes unfolded
under completely different circumstances.
The United Flight lost
its hydraulics over one
of the flattest parts of the United States
while Japan Airlines found
itself over mountainous terrain.
They were flying different aircraft
with vastly different mass
and control characteristics.
And crucially, Japan Airlines
had lost its vertical
stabilizer, a failure
that made a controlled
landing physically impossible.
And the fact that the crew managed
to keep the aircraft in the air
for over half an hour is
nothing short of extraordinary.
(happy music)
But what these two
incidents do have in common
is that they reveal just
how catastrophic the loss
of all hydraulics can be.
And they also have
something else in common.
To this day, both incidents
are regarded as some
of the most remarkable
examples of pilot skill.
United 232 is often cited as
one of the clearest examples
of crew resource management in action,
a captain, first officer, flight engineer,
and even a training captain
all working together,
sharing control inputs and
communicating constantly.
(pensive music)
But aviation didn't
always operate that way.
And, in fact, the culture
that made that kind
of collaboration possible
was born out of tragedy.
One famous example of bad
communication leading to tragedy
is the Tenerife disaster in 1977
when two 747s filled with passengers
collided almost head on on the runway,
the absolute worst case scenario.
(flight engineer speaking
in foreign language)
(captain speaking in foreign language)
(flight engineer speaking
in foreign language)
- And to understand how this happened,
I created a full-length video
detailing the exact radio exchanges
and mapping out the chain of events
that led to the collision.
This video is part of an entire series
of videos I created
called "Under Exposure."
In this series, I created
in-depth documentaries
about high-stakes events
that reshaped our world.
And this series is exclusive to Nebula,
which is a streaming
service that I am building
to gather with other like-minded creators.
Now, the idea behind Nebula
is to let creators you
already watch on YouTube
make the stuff they really wanna make,
bigger, higher budget,
and without relying on ads
with exclusive films and
documentaries from me,
Wendover Productions, Tom Scott,
Lindsay Ellis, Real Engineering,
and many, many more.
So go to nebula.tv/neo
and make sure you use exactly this link
to get 50% off an annual subscription.
That brings it down to just $30 a year
to access all the
amazing videos on Nebula.
And as always, thanks for the support
and thank you so much
for watching this video.